Guide to the Patricia Murphy Derian Papers, 1962-2008 and undated RL.00305
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Post-Carter Administration Human Rights Work Series, 1978-2007 and undated, 8 boxes
  - Prizes and Awards Subseries, 1981-2004
    Relates to Derian's work on committees. Particularly significant are the State Department documents, correspondence and articles regarding the controversy around the Robert F. Kennedy Human Rights Award given to Co-Madres of El Salvador in 1984 who were denied visas by the State Department to enter the U.S. for the award ceremony on the grounds that they had links with leftist terrorists. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    - Carter-Menil HR Foundation Prize and Rothko Chapel Awards, 1981-1986 and undated (Box 13)
    - Carter-Menil HR Foundation Prize, 1987-1992 (Box 13)
    - Carter-Menil HR Foundation Prize, review of nominees, 1990-1994 (Box 13)
    - Grawemeyer Award for Ideas Improving World Order, 1998-2004 (Box 13)
    - Letelier-Moffitt Memorial Human Rights Award, 1983-1984 (Box 13)
    - MacArthur Foundation Fellowships 1982, 1988-1989 (Box 13)
    - Oscar Romeo Award, 1990 (Box 13)
    - Robert F. Kennedy Book Awards, 1982 (Box 13)
    - Robert F. Kennedy Memorial Human Rights Award, 1983-1984 (Box 13)
    - Robert F. Kennedy Memorial - judges/international advisory committee, 1988 (Box 13)
    - Robert F. Kennedy Human Rights Award - judging process/criteria, 1984 (Box 13)
    - Robert F. Kennedy Human Rights Award, 1984: Co-Madres of El Salvador, 1984 and undated (Box 13)
    - Robert F. Kennedy Human Rights Award, 1985-1990s, 8 folders (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Material Subseries, 1980-2007 and undated
    Materials such as articles, dissertation monographs, reports, correspondence, political posters and news clippings refer to diverse issues such as human rights and the Bush administration, women's rights, U.S. foreign policy, and evaluations of the political and human rights situation in various Latin American countries. Arranged in original order as received.
    - George W. Bush administration, 2003-2007 (Box 14)
    - Central America - correspondence, 1981-1989 (Box 14)
    - Central America - articles, 1980-1989 (Box 14)
    - Derian's notes on Central America, undated (Box 14)
    - Latin America articles, 1980-2004 (Box 14)
    - Latin America - documents and articles, 1982-1987 (Box 14)
    - Latin America - correspondence, 1981-2002 (Box 14)
    - Foreign policy - correspondence, 1981-2005 (Box 14)
    - Foreign policy - documents, 1983-2003 (Box 14)
    - Foreign policy - articles, 1980-2006 (Box 14)
    - Foreign Policy and Human Rights during the Carter Administration, B.A. Thesis by Mark S. Mahaney, 1987 (Box 14)
    - Women - articles, 1981-2003 (Box 14)
    - Women - correspondence, 1981-2003 (Box 14)
    - Women's National Democratic Club - Address by Philip M. Kaiser, 1982 Dec. 2 (Box 14)
    - National security - articles, 1981-1987 and undated (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous articles, 1987-2007 and undated (Box 14)
    - Preliminary research done with Tex Harris, 1996-2007 and undated (Box 14)
    - Posters, Latin America related to human rights issues, 3 items (Box 14)
- Countries Series, 1976-2007 and undated, 9 boxes
  Brings together materials relating specifically to a country or geographical area, ranging widely over Derian's career - several decades in most cases - and featuring significant human rights issues of the time. Materials across folders typically consist of correspondence, Derian's trip notes, reports, unclassified documents, news clippings, and other print material, including posters and flyers. Arranged into subseries by country: Argentina, El Salvador, Chile, Cuba, Guatemala, Honduras, Nicaragua, Paraguay, South Korea, Vietnam, and "Middle Eastern Countries." El Salvador files form the largest group, with Argentina, Nicaragua, and South Korea close behind. Much smaller groups are found for Cuba, Honduras, Venezuela, and Guatemala. A final grouping, Miscellaneous Countries, is made up of folders on sixteen other nations. Arranged alphabetically by country, and within, roughly in alphabetical order by file title, as received.
  Various related material on these countries also found in the Department of State Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs Bureau Series, and the Post-Carter Administration Human Rights Work Series.
  - Argentina, 1981-2007 and undated
    - "Las Madres de Plaza de Mayo," 1984-1985 (Box 15)
    - Alfonsin, Raul, Inauguration of, 1983, 1983 Dec and undated (Box 15)
    - National Library Award, 2001 and undated (Box 15)
    - 30th Anniversary of military coup, 2006 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1993-1994, 1998 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 2000-2007, 8 folders (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 15)
    - Department of State documents (Box 15)
    - Publishing with Tex Harris, 2001-2007 (Box 15)
    - Flyers, 1987 (Box 15)
  - El Salvador, 1979-2005 and undated
    - Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 16)
    - R. Cohen Notes - transition, 1980-1981 (Box 16)
    - R. Cohen Notes - killings of nuns (Box 16)
    - R. Cohen Notes - human rights, 1980-1984 (Box 16)
    - R. Cohen Notes - aid, 1980-1984 (Box 16)
    - National Security Archive documents, 1979-1984 (Box 16)
    - Report to the Lawyers Committee for Human Rights on Jesuits murder trial, 1991 (Box 16)
    - Ford v. Garcia Trial - proceedings, 2000 Oct. 10 - Nov. 11 2000 (Box 16)
    - Ford v. Garcia Trial - Patricia Derian testimony materials, 2000-2001 and undated (Box 16)
    - Ford v. Garcia Trial - articles, 1998-2000 (Box 16)
    - Romagoza Case, 2003-2005 (Box 16)
    - Archbishop Romero trial materials, 2004 (Box 16)
    - Co-Madres materials, 1985-1988 (Box 16)
    - Commission on United States Central American Relations documents re: El Salvador, 1983 and undated (Box 16)
    - Freedom House Delegation, 1994 Feb. 12-18 (Box 16)
    - Freedom House report on 1994 elections, 1994 and undated (Box 16)
    - Articles - history of the conflict, 1981-1982 and undated (Box 16)
    - Transition, 1980-1981 and undated (Box 17)
    - Civil War, 1980-1982 and undated (Box 17)
    - Civil War, 1983 (Box 17)
    - Civil War, 1994-1992 (Box 17)
    - Elections, 1981-1982 and undated (Box 17)
    - Elections, 1983 (Box 17)
    - Elections, 1984-1989 (Box 17)
    - José Napoleón Duarte, 1984-1988 (Box 17)
    - Land reform, 1980-1987 and undated (Box 17)
    - U.S. foreign policy, 1980-1991 and undated, 5 folders (Box 17)
    - El Salvador in international politics (Box 17)
    - U.S. foreign aid, 1980-1982 (Box 17)
    - U.S. foreign aid, 1983 (Box 17)
    - U.S. foreign aid, 1984-1990 (Box 17)
    - Human rights, 1980-1981 (Box 17)
    - Human rights, 1982 (Box 17)
    - Human rights, 1983 (Box 17)
    - Human rights, 1984-1985 (Box 18)
    - Human rights, 1986-1989 (Box 18)
    - Killings of American nuns, 1980-1985 (Box 18)
    - Death squads, 1981-1993 (Box 18)
    - Jesuit deaths, 1989-1993 (Box 18)
    - Archbishop Oscar Arnulfo Romero killing, 1983-1989 (Box 18)
    - Truth Commissions, 1991-1993 (Box 18)
    - Journalism, 1981-1982 (Box 18)
    - Similarities with Vietnam War, 1982-1983 (Box 18)
    - Refugees to the U.S., 1982-1983 (Box 18)
  - Chile, 1976-2004 and undated
    - Correspondence, 1978-2003 (Box 18)
    - Operation Condor and Letelier, Moffitt murder investigation materials, 1976-2004 (Box 18)
    - Kissinger and Pinochet research by L. Komisar, 1999 (Box 18)
    - Pinochet case articles, 1998 and undated (Box 18)
    - Fernandez - Larios trial, 2003 (Box 18)
    - Chile articles, 1977-2003 (Box 18)
  - Cuba, 1980-2006 and undated
    - Cuba correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 18)
    - Commission on United States, Central American Relations delegation to Cuba, 1984 Oct. 13-18 (Box 18)
    - Roger Plant paper on Cuba situation, undated (Box 18)
    - Cuba articles and conference proceedings, 1980-2006 (Box 18)
  - Guatemala, 1980-2004 and undated
    - Guatemala correspondence, 1980-1986 and undated (Box 18)
    - Myrna Mack Chang case and inter-American court, 1983, 2003-2004 (Box 18)
    - Guatemala documents, 1988-2005 (Box 18)
  - Honduras, 1986-2001
    - Honduras correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 18)
    - Honduras articles, 1993-2001 (Box 18)
  - Nicaragua, 1981-1988
    - Nicaragua correspondence, 1981-1987 (Box 19)
    - Leiken, New Republic, Reform the Contras, 1986 Mar. 31 (Box 19)
    - Shea, New Republic Human Rights in Nicaragua, 1986 Sept. 1 (Box 19)
    - Leiken, New York Review of Books, Tangled Nicaragua: An Exchange, and Battle for Nicaragua, 1985-1988 (Box 19)
    - Jerkins and Patricia Derian, New York Review of Books, Tangled Nicaragua: An Exchange, 1987 (Box 19)
    - Leiken statement before the Committee on Foreign Relations, 1986-1987 and undated (Box 19)
    - Alexander Cockburn - Nation, The Political Uses of Human Rights, 1986 (Box 19)
    - Robert S. Leiken, Washington Post, Who Says Contras Cannot Succeed?, 1988 (Box 19)
    - Nicaragua trip, 1986 (Box 19)
    - International League for Human Rights correspondence, 1986 and undated (Box 19)
    - International League for Human Rights report draft on human rights defenders in Nicaragua, I, 1986 (Box 19)
    - International League for Human Rights report draft on human rights defenders in Nicaragua, II, 1986 (Box 19)
    - Human rights reports re: Nicaragua, 1 of 3, 1985-1987 (Box 20)
    - Human rights reports re: Nicaragua, 2 of 3, 1985-1987 (Box 20)
    - Human rights reports re: Nicaragua, 3 of 3, 1985-1987 (Box 20)
  - Paraguay, 1978-2005
    - Paraguay correspondence, 1986-2003 (Box 20)
    - Paraguay articles, 1980-1987 (Box 20)
    - America Watch delegation materials, 1986 (Box 20)
    - America Watch delegation notes, 1986 (Box 20)
    - Reports on the situation of human rights in Paraguay, 1978, 1987 (Box 20)
    - Amnesty International Paraguay Urgent Action Network correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 20)
    - Filartiga v. Pena materials, 1980-2005 (Box 20)
  - Venezuela, 1994
    - Venezuela trip, 1994 Mar. 2-5 (Box 20)
  - South Korea, 1980-1998 and undated
    - Korea correspondence, 1984-1995 (Box 21)
    - Delegation to Korea with Kim Dae Jung, 1 of 3, 1985 (Box 21)
    - Delegation to Korea with Kim Dae Jung, 2 of 3, 1985 (Box 21)
    - Delegation to Korea with Kim Dae Jung, 3 of 3, 1985 (Box 21)
    - Kim Dae Jung - plans for return, 1984-1985 (Box 21)
    - Concerns re: Kim Dae Jung's return, 1984-1985 (Box 21)
    - Events in Korea prior to Kim Dae Jung's return, 1985 (Box 21)
    - Kim Dae Jung delegation's arrival at Kimpo, 1985 (Box 21)
    - Korea articles - Kim Dae Jung, 1980 (Box 21)
    - Korea Articles - aftermath of Kim Dae Jung's return and blame, 1985 and undated (Box 21)
    - Columns by Patricia Derian, 1985 and undated (Box 21)
    - Korea articles - election and ban on opposition leaders, 1985 (Box 21)
    - Korea articles - American-Korean relations, 1985 (Box 21)
    - Korea documents and interviews, 1983-1987 and undated (Box 21)
    - FDL-AP Inaugural Conference and Kim Dae Jung's Presidential Inauguration, 1994-1998 (Box 21)
    - 10th Anniversary of North American Coalition for Human Rights in Korea, 1985 (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous Korea materials, undated (Box 21)
  - Vietnam, 1977-2005 and undated
    - Vietnam correspondence, 1977-2005 (Box 22)
    - Letters from women and children in detention centers, 1989-1990 and undated (Box 22)
    - Women's Commission for Refugee Women and Children (WCRWC), 1989-1990 and undated (Box 22)
    - WCRWC delegation materials, 1989-1990 and undated (Box 22)
    - Draft of WCRWC report, 1990 (Box 22)
    - Vietnam articles, 1978-1994 (Box 22)
    - Indochina Resource Action Center delegation to Hong Kong, 1990 and undated (Box 22)
  - Middle Eastern Countries, 1978-2006 and undated
    - Middle East general, 1988-1992 and undated (Box 22)
    - Iran, 1978-1997 and undated (Box 22)
    - Iraq, 1989-2005 and undated (Box 22)
    - Israel-Palestine, 1980-2006 and undated (Box 22)
    - Kuwait, 1980-1992 and undated (Box 22)
    - Saudi Arabia, 1982, 1986-1988 (Box 22)
    - Helsinki Watch delegation to Turkey, 1984 Sept., 1984-1987 and undated (Box 22)
    - Turkey articles, 1980 (Box 22)
    - Yemen, 2003-2006 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous Countries, 1976-2007 and undated
    - Cambodia, 1980, 1991 (Box 23)
    - China, 1980, 1994 (Box 23)
    - Haiti, 1982-1994 (Box 23)
    - India, 1985-1991 and undated (Box 23)
    - Indonesia, 1978, 1990, 1995 and undated (Box 23)
    - Jamaica, 1980 (Box 23)
    - Liberia, 1980, 1985 and undated (Box 23)
    - Nepal, 1985, 1990 and undated (Box 23)
    - Pakistan, 1981-1987 and undated (Box 23)
    - Panama, 1988, 1994 and undated (Box 23)
    - Peru, 1986, 1989, 2000 (Box 23)
    - Philippines correspondence, 1983-1990 (Box 23)
    - Assassination of Benigno Aquino, 1983 (Box 23)
    - Philippines articles, 1978-1982 (Box 23)
    - Poland, 1980 (Box 23)
    - Singapore articles and publications, 2000-2007 (Box 23)
    - Alliance for Reform and Democracy in Asia - delegation to Singapore, 2004-2005 (Box 23)
    - South Africa, 1976-2001 and undated (Box 23)
    - Uruguay, 1980-1993 (Box 23)
    - USSR correspondence, 1978-1989 (Box 23)
    - USSR articles and documents, 1978-1989 (Box 23)
    - Andrei Sakharov materials, 1977, 1984 and undated (Box 23)
    - IPS Delegation to US-USSR Bilateral Relations Exchange, 1994 (Box 23)
    - Other countries, 1979-2007 and undated (Box 23)
- Audiovisual Material, 1977-2004 and undated, 1 box
  Contains audio and video recordings of Derian's public speeches, interviews and excerpts from political protests in Argentina, dated between the years 1977 and 2004. Formats include fourteen audio cassettes, six video cassettes (U-Matic, VHS and Beta) and two CD-ROMs. The latter contain footage of interviews as part of the project Proyecto Archivo Oral. Arranged in original order as received. Titles are from original labels.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [Original audiovisual material CLOSED to use. A use copy must be made before contents can be accessed. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Las Madres, excerpts [Betamax] (Box 24)
  - Patt Derian, Miami, Fl, 2004 Mar. 19 [VHS] (Box 24)
  - Unmarked video [Umatic] (Box 24)
  - CNN, Freeman Reports, visas denied to political activist, 1984 Dec. 4 [Umatic] (Box 24)
  - CNN, Freeman Reports, human rights report card 1980, 1981 Feb. 11 [Umatic] (Box 24)
  - Human Rights, 1981, work tape [Umatic] (Box 24)
  - NBC News, Patt Derian speech [Umatic] (Box 24)
  - Proyecto Archivo Oral, Patricia Derian, 2001 Aug. 6 [CD-ROM], 2 items (Box 24)
  - CD, Otras Voces De La Historia, Exhibicion Virtual [CD-ROM] (Box 24)
  - National Security, 1983 May 1 [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - Acquino Assassination, 1983 Nov. 14 [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - Communique, NPR, 1981 Jan. 2 [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - SIS Lecture, 1981 Mar. 25 [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - Press Conference, 1978 Aug. 16 [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - Cantata Las Madres en la Plaza, 1983 [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - Conversation with Jeff Merritt of Columbia University, 1983 Feb. 17 [Audio cassette], 2 items (Box 24)
  - National Security, host Ian Masters, 1985 July 14 [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - Face the Nation, CBS Radio, 1977 Dec. 25 [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - Open Forum, State Department, 1982 Sept. 22 [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - ALA IWY, 1977 July [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - Special Address to the Inter-American Defense College, 1978 Apr. 11 [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
  - Argentina human rights [Audio cassette] (Box 24)
- Oversize Material, 1976-2007, 1 folder
  Posters, flyers, and other items removed from files throughout the collection.
  - Poster, Women Presidential Appointees by the Carter Administration, 1979 July, 19x29" (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Poster, Somoza Bombs His Own People, undated, 17x24" (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Poster, 25th Anniversary of the Palestinian Revolution, Supporters of Palestine National Liberation Movement 'FAT'H' February 4, 1990, 11x17.5" (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Symposium Poster, 9x24" (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Posters Latin America, human rights-related, approx. 19x13", 3 items (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Flyer, 8.5x14" (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Poster, Medios de Comunicacion Valorizando a la Mujer, 12x15" (Oversize-folder 1)
  - 1/500,000 Tactical Pilotage Chart of El Salvador, Honduras, Nicaragua (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Poster, refers to Napoleon Ortigoza, undated, 14x20.5" (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Poster, about Yuri Orlov by Helsinki Watch, undated, 17x22" (Oversize-folder 1)
  - No Smoking posters, 2 items (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Abuelas de Plaza de Mayo (Oversize-folder 2)